Duncan Emrich Manuscript Collection, 1933-1977
Library of Congress American Folklife Center Archive of Folk Culture
Duncan Emrich Manuscript Collection, 1933-1977 1950-1969
AFC 1977/007
Archive of Folk Culture, American Folklife Center, Library of Congress Washington, D.C.
(original) 8.75 linear feet (21 boxes) including manuscripts and 23 black-and-white photographic prints
Emrich, Duncan, 1908-1977
Correspondence, research materials, book contracts, and typescripts for several of author and folklorist Duncan Emrich's published and unpublished books and articles on American folklore. There are some personal papers, including Emrich's college transcripts; course materials from classes that Emrich taught at the University of Maryland; and documents pertaining to Emrich's service with the Supreme Headquarters Allied Expeditionary Force during World War II, and the Department of State, United States Information Agency during the 1960s. Book projects include American Folk Poetry; song lyrics prepared for An Anthology of American Folk Songs, with Charles Seeger; the Lucius Beebe Reader, with Charles Clegg; a Child's Book of Folklore, with Marion V. Emrich and George Korson; poetry and articles about the American West; and unpublished works on animal lore, death, and other topics. The collection includes a bibliography of Emrich's writings, and a Bibliography of American Folksong in the English Language compiled by Joseph C. Hickerson, galleys, photographs of Duncan Emrich, fan mail from children, and other materials.
Selected Search Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the LC Catalog. They are grouped by name of person or organization, by subject or location, and by occupation and listed alphabetically.
People
Beebe, Lucius.; Clegg, Charles, 1916-1979. Lucius Beebe reader.; Emrich, Duncan, 1908-1977, collector, author.; Emrich, Duncan, 1908-1977--Correspondence.; Emrich, Duncan, 1908-1977--Written works.; Emrich, Duncan, 1908-1977. American folk poetry: an anthology; Emrich, Duncan, 1908-1977. Whim-wham book.; Emrich, Marion Vallat, 1909-2006. The child's book of folklore.; Hickerson, Joseph C. (Joseph Charles), 1935- Bibliography of American folksong.; Hyatt, Harry Middleton, 1890- --Correspondence.; Seeger, Charles, 1886-1979.
Subjects
American poetry--20th century.; Children--United States--Folklore.; Folk literature--United States.; Folk poetry, American.; Folk songs, English--Texts.; Folk songs, English--United States.; Folklore--United States--History and criticism.; Folklore--West (U.S.); Folklorists--United States--Correspondence.; Games--United States--20th century.; World War, 1939-1945--Veterans.
Places
West (U.S.)--Social life and customs.
Form/Genre
Bibliographies.; Clippings.; Contracts.; Correspondence.; Manuscripts for publication.; Photographic prints.; Poems.; Poetry.
Arrangement
Arranged into the following series:
Series 1: Administrative Files
Series 2: Correspondence
Series 3: Personal Papers
Series 4: Articles
Series 5: Student Papers
Series 6: Published and Unpublished Books
Series 7: Graphic Images
Oversize Materials
Acquisition
Donated by Marion Vallat Emrich, 1977.
Access and Restrictions
Collection is open for research. To request materials, please contact the Folklife Reading Room at http://hdl.loc.gov/loc.afc/folklife.contact
Related Material
Duncan Emrich Papers, American University Library, Washington D.C.
Biographical Note
Duncan Emrich was born on April 11, 1908, in Mardin, Turkey. His parents, Richard and Jeannette Emrich, were both missionaries stationed in Turkey. At the onset of World War I, and the widespread massacres occurring within the area, the family was forced to flee. They returned to the United States and settled in New England where Emrich attended Phillips Academy, in Andover, Massachusetts. Emrich received his B.A. from Brown University, an M.A. from Columbia University, and in 1934 he received a Doctor en Letras in medieval Spanish and Arabic from the University of Madrid (Spain). In 1937, he earned his Ph.D. from Harvard under the direction of George Lyman Kittredge. Emrich furthered his studies by conducting postdoctoral studies at the Sorbonne, University of Paris; University of Aix-en-Provence; University of Nancy; University of Cologne; and Escuela de Estudios Arabes in Granada, Spain.
Emrich’s teaching career began in at Columbia University, where he taught English from 1937-1940. He then moved to Denver, Colorado, and became the assistant professor of English at the University of Denver from 1940-1942. It was at this institution that Emrich’s passion for folklore materialized. Upon his arrival at the University of Denver, Emrich spent most of his time in the campus library where he became interested in Old West mining camp lore, the focus of many of his future writings. In addition, it was in the Blood saloon in Virginia City, Nevada, where he heard a miner bellow "Who shot Maggie in the freckle?" that he gained the inspiration to write his first ballad of the same name.
In 1942, Emrich left his teaching position and enrolled in the Army Command and General Staff School at Fort Leavenworth, Kansas. He emerged as a lieutenant with an assignment to the U.S. Army military intelligence unit in Washington D.C., serving in England, France, and Germany. Shortly thereafter, Emrich won the Croix de Guerre for his service in France. Emrich then achieved the rank of major after being assigned as the official American historian to General Eisenhower where he was commissioned to write a contemporary account of the war in Europe.
After the war, Emrich settled in Washington D.C., and from 1945-1955, was head of the Archive of Folk Song at the Library of Congress and chief of the Folklore Section. During his tenure at the Library, Emrich was awarded a Guggenheim (1948-1950) and a Fulbright Fellowship (1952-1953). As a Fulbright lecturer to Italy, Emrich travelled to the universities of Rome, Naples, Messina, and Palermo lecturing on American civilization. From 1953-1955 Emrich hosted a weekly radio show on folklore called "Weekend" on the National Broadcasting Co. The show brought national attention to the Library of Congress where folk sayings, proverbs, tongue twisters and the like were discussed, shared and contributed by radio listeners. The radio show generated a large amount of handwritten correspondence from listeners including children.
Emrich was also instrumental in the growth of the American Folklore Society in Washington and the Junior Folklore Club where membership began from age ten and up. In 1955 Emrich resigned from the Library of Congress to become the cultural affairs officer with the American Embassies in Greece, India, and Togo. In 1966, after returning from Africa, he worked with the U.S. Information Agency in Washington D.C. until 1969, when he returned to teaching as an adjunct professor of American folklore at American University.
In his determination to deliver folklore to the public, Emrich hosted a series of annual lectures at American University. To support this venture he established the American Folklore Fund. Emrich’s genuine interest in folklore resonated in the work he contributed to the field. He viewed folklore as a combination of tradition, history, and antique curiosities. According to his lifelong friend Horace Beck, "at a time when nationalism was against the norm Emrich believed in it. He believed that folklore was to be collected, preserved and enjoyed not only by scholars but by the general public." This school of thought can be seen in the works Emrich produced. He authored and co-authored a series of published and unpublished books, articles, and poems, including American Folk Poetry and the Whim Wham Book.
He received numerous prizes from both Brown and Harvard Universities and, in 1970, his book entitled The Nonsense Book received six awards. Hodgepodge Book was named Outstanding Children's Book by the New York Times Book Review in 1972. His Folklore on the American Land was used as an introductory text for American folklore studies.
At the time of his death Emrich was working, ironically, on a book entitled, The Book of Death. Emrich died on August 23, 1977.
Scope and Content Note
The collection includes correspondence, research materials, book contracts, and typescripts for several of author and folklorist Duncan Emrich's published and unpublished books and articles on American folklore. There are some personal papers, including Emrich's college transcripts; course materials from classes that Emrich taught at the University of Maryland; and documents pertaining to Emrich's service with the Supreme Headquarters Allied Expeditionary Force during World War II, and the Department of State, United States Information Agency during the 1960s. Book projects include American Folk Poetry; song lyrics prepared for An Anthology of American Folk Songs, with Charles Seeger; the Lucius Beebe Reader, with Charles Clegg; a Child's Book of Folklore, by Marion V. Emrich and George Korson; Duncan Emrich's poetry and articles about the American West; and unpublished works on animal lore, death, and other topics. The collection includes a bibliography of Emrich's writings, and a Bibliography of American Folksong in the English Language compiled by Joseph C. Hickerson; galleys, photographs of Duncan Emrich, fan mail from children, and other materials. Correspondents include Roger D. Abrahams, Horace Beck, Jan Brunvand, Ellsworth Bunker, Kenneth Clark, Frank Dobie, Richard M. Dorson, Lydia Fish, Kenneth S. Goldstein, Percy Grainger, Wayland D. Hand, Harry M. Hyatt, Louis C. Jones, Barbara Kirshenblatt-Gimblett, Sarah Gertrude Knott, Maud Gentry Long, Archibald MacLeish, Lynwood Montell, Vance Randolph, Barre Toelken, Francis Lee Utley, and Frank Warner, among others.
Selected Works in the Collection
Emrich, Marion Vallat and George Korson, eds. The Child’s Book of Folklore. New York: Dial Press, 1947.
Emrich, Duncan. Comstock Bonanza: Western Americana of J. Ross Browne, Mark Twain, Sam Davis, Bret Harte, James W. Gally, Dan de Quille, Joseph T. Goodman [and] Fred Hart. New York: Vanguard Press. 1950.
Emrich, Duncan. Folklore of the American Land. Boston: Little Brown, 1952.
Emrich, Duncan. Cowboy’s Own Brand Book. New York: Crowell. 1954.
Emrich, Duncan, Charles Clegg, eds. The Lucius Beebe Reader. New York: Doubleday, 1967.
Emrich, Duncan. Folklore of Love and Courtship. New York: American Heritage Press, 1970.
Emrich, Duncan. Folklore of Weddings and Marriage. New York: American Heritage Press, 1970.
Emrich, Duncan. Book of Wishes and Wishmaking. New York: Four Winds. 1971.
Emrich, Duncan. American Folk Poetry: An Anthology. Boston: Little Brown, 1974.
Emrich, Duncan. The Whim Wham Book. New York: Four Winds Press, 1975.
Selected Unpublished Works in the Collection
Emrich, Duncan and Marion Vallat Emrich. A Book of Western Lore for Young People.
Emrich, Duncan and Charles Seeger. An Anthology of American Folksong.
Emrich, Marion Vallat and Duncan Emrich. Animal Lore.
Emrich, Duncan. Book of Death.
Container List
- Series 1: Administrative Files
  - Finding Aid, 22 pages. (Box-folder 1/1)
  - Bibliography of Emrich’s Writings: 1932-1974. Compiled by Margaret R. Thomas. A bound copy of Duncan Emrich’s writings from 1932-1974., 31 pages. (Box-folder 1/2)
  - Photo Duplication Order Forms/Reprint Permissions. Undated. American Folklore Society schedule of fees for reprinting publications and the Library of Congress photo duplication forms., 16 pages. (Box-folder 1/3)
  - Marion Emrich Deed of Gift. March 22, 1993. Correspondence between Emrich and Donald Panzera pertaining to a collection of Children’s Book of Folklore which was gifted to the Library of Congress., 8 pages. (Box-folder 1/4)
- Series 2: Correspondence
  - Abrahams, Roger D. December 6, [year unknown] To Duncan Emrich from the African and Afro-American Research Institute, the University of Texas at Austin., 1 page. (Box-folder 2/5)
  - American Heritage Press. June 1969-December 1971 Between American Heritage Press and Duncan Emrich concerning the book reviews for the Book of Wishes and Wishmaking., 13 pages. (Box-folder 2/6)
  - American National Red Cross (Editor, Red Cross Youth Publications). February 19, 1974 Between Mary Ellen Hughes, editor for the Red Cross Youth Publications, and Duncan Emrich concerning the submission for his article, "If Wishes Were Fishes.", 10 pages. (Box-folder 2/7)
  - Anderson, Charles R. January 31, 1971; March 19, 1971 Between Charles Anderson and Duncan Emrich for permission to include three songs, which Anderson and his friend Genie sang for the Library of Congress in 1947, in Emrich’s book Folklore on the American Land., 3 pages. (Box-folder 2/8)
  - Beagle, Peter S. August 7, 1969 Between Peter Beagle and Duncan Emrich concerning literature about the existence of unicorns., 1 page. (Box-folder 2/9)
  - Beck, Horace. January 24, 1972 Horace Beck provides feedback to Emrich about a folklore book Emrich wrote a review to Little, Brown and Co. on Emrich’s behalf., 2 pages. (Box-folder 2/10)
  - Bisbee, John B. March 5, 1965 To Duncan Emrich from John Bisbee as he sought a repository for two handwritten diaries from his grandmother Martha Gally, the wife of James W. Gally, when they lived in Hot Creek, Nevada, with excerpts of the book, Comstock Bonanza., 24 pages. (Box-folder 2/11)
  - Blotner, Joseph L. March-May, 1967 To Duncan Emrich thanking him for his assistance with the Faulkner Collection and arranging to meet Emrich., 5 pages. (Box-folder 2/12)
  - Blumenstock, Mrs. February 8, 1971 To Mrs. Blumenstock thanking her for permissions., 2 pages. (Box-folder 2/13)
  - Boswell, George W. March 13, 1972 George Boswell thanking and requesting Emrich to send manuscript for him to edit., 1 page. (Box-folder 2/14)
  - Bronson, Bertrand H. December 2, 1972 Bertrand Bronson provides some editorial corrections for Emrich’s book., 1 page. (Box-folder 2/15)
  - Browne, Ray. October 10, 1969 Request to use a few excerpts from Duncan’s article, "Beliefs from Alabama.", 1 page. (Box-folder 2/16)
  - Brunvand. Jan-February 2, 1972 Jan Brunvand praises Emrich’s book, Folklore on the American Land. He also suggests the possibility to explore other urban tales., 1 page. (Box-folder 2/17)
  - Bunker, Ellsworth Ambassador, New Delhi, India. September 27, 1960 Ambassor Bunker expressing his gratitude that Emrich performed with Indo-American Society of Calcutta., 1 page. (Box-folder 2/18)
  - Butterfield, Roger. August 15, 1970 Antiquarian bookseller, Roger Butterfield writes to Duncan., 1 page. (Box-folder 2/19)
  - The Clarendon Press (Oxford). September 6, 1967 Editorial responses., 3 pages. (Box-folder 2/20)
  - Clarke, Kenneth. February 16, 1971, February 21, 1972 Responses to Emrich’s book., 4 pages. (Box-folder 2/21)
  - Clayton, Cecil D. November 22, 1976 Cecil Clayton offers an alternative to a chorus Duncan composed and relates a story about folk medicine., 1 page. (Box-folder 2/22)
  - Boatright, Mody C. April 15 Mody Boatright updates Emrich with his latest book collaboration., 1 page. (Box-folder 2/23)
  - Clegg, Charles (Chuck). July 16, 1967 Emrich submits some changes to the Lucius Beebe Reader., 2 pages. (Box-folder 2/24)
  - Columbia University Press. December 6, 1969 Duncan Emrich writes to Columbia University Press requesting the permission to use material from Vance Randolph’s Ozark Superstitions in his books, The Folklore of Love and Courtship and The Folklore of Marriage., 1 page. (Box-folder 2/25)
  - Dobie, Frank. January 28, 1952 Frank Dobie writes to Duncan about the contents in Comstock Bonanza., 2 pages. (Box-folder 2/26)
  - Nafi, Archivist. The Hartford Seminary Foundation (Conn.). July 8, 1969 To Duncan Emrich with thanks for the materials he submitted towards the Duncan Black Macdonald collection and also informing him of the correspondence between his parents and Macdonald. There are three leaves of handwritten correspondence written on the verso and recto to Macdonald from Emrich’s father and five pages from a book written about Duncan Black Macdonald., 25 pages. (Box-folder 2/27)
  - Dorson, Richard. November 22, 1971 Letter from Richard Dorson to Mrs. Leslie Wakefield of Little, Brown and Company rejecting Duncan’s book on Folklore on the American Land as a college text book. Second letter from Dorson to Emrich requesting his assistance for two of Dorson’s students., 2 pages. (Box-folder 2/28)
  - Epstein, Linda. June 21, 1971 Student requesting independent study with Duncan Emrich., 1 page. (Box-folder 2/29)
  - Fish, Lydia. March 6, 1972; August. 9, 1973 Between colleagues in the field of folklore., 3 pages. (Box-folder 2/30)
  - Four Winds Press. 1968-1976 Correspondence and transcript for Emrich’s books., 20 pages. (Box-folder 2/31)
  - Frederick A Praeger, Inc. June 9, 1967 Correspondence and transcript of a rejected proposal to do a book on Italian ex-voto., 4 pages. (Box-folder 2/32)
  - Goldstein, Kenneth S. March 11, 1971 Pertaining to the inclusion of material from the Journal of American Folklore in Emrich’s book., 4 pages. (Box-folder 2/33)
  - Grainger, Percy. June 29, 1949 Congratulating Emrich on the work he did with Danish folk songs., 1 page. (Box-folder 2/34)
  - Hand, Wayland D. November 3, 1970 - Feb. 7, 1977 Between colleagues in the field of folklore., 4 pages. (Box-folder 2/35)
  - Harder, Leslie. January 29, 1971, January 31, 1972 Between Harder and Emrich as Harder updates him on his sabbatical to Poland and Emrich requests permission for material to include in his book., 2 pages. (Box-folder 2/36)
  - Harper and Brothers (Frank MacGregor, Pres.). Dec. 18, 1950; April 2, 1951. Emrich requesting permission to use MacGregor’s Mark Twain material in his book., 2 pages. (Box-folder 2/37)
  - Harvard University (Florence K. Leetch, Appointment Office). April 20, 1968 Acceptance for appointment at the University of Nevada., 1 page. (Box-folder 2/38)
  - Hillard, Sandy Adams. Undated Request for review and advice for book written by Sandy Hillard’s husband., 1 page. (Box-folder 2/39)
  - Hyatt, Harry M. January 13, 1970-March 7, 1972 Permission request for using material for Emrich’s book; with a galley for Hyatt’s book Hoodoo-Conjuration Witchcraft-Rootwork., 6 pages. (Box-folder 2/40)
  - John Cushman Associates, Inc. 1967-1971 Correspondence pertaining to Emrich’s books with Cushman Associates., 10 pages. (Box-folder 2/41)
  - Jones, Louis Clark. 1967 -1972 Correspondence pertaining to Emrich’s folklore career., 6 pages. (Box-folder 2/42)
  - Jones, Thelma Gray. December 29, 1971 Jones’ response to accepting to write a piece for Emrich., 1 page. (Box-folder 2/43)
  - Kanter, Hal. September 1, 1971-May 9, 1971 Hal Kanter’s new show and personal correspondence., 4 pages. (Box-folder 2/44)
  - Keystone Folklore Quarterly (Robert Byington, Exec. Sec). January 24, 1971 Permission for the inclusion of two articles in Emrich’s book, Folklore on the American Land., 1 page. (Box-folder 2/45)
  - Kirkland, Edwin C. May 22, 1968 Recommendation letter to the University of Nevada on behalf of Duncan Emrich., 1 page. (Box-folder 2/46)
  - Kirshenblatt-Gimblett, Barbara to Junior Folklore Club. November 10, 1976 Requesting information on membership: the Junior Folklore Club., 1 page. (Box-folder 2/47)
  - Knott, Sarah Gertrude. February 14, 19- Congratulatory letter., 2 pages. (Box-folder 2/48)
  - Koch, William E. Undated Address of William Koch., 1 page. (Box-folder 2/49)
  - Land, Robert H. (Library of Congress). September 4, 1968 Letter accompanied by Library of Congress photo duplication permission forms., 3 pages. (Box-folder 2/50)
  - Lawrence County American Revolution Bicentennial Commission, (Lawrenceburg, Tenn.). February 8, 1977 Correspondence indicating interest in folklore., 17 pages. (Box-folder 2/51)
  - Little, Brown and Company Publishers 1967-1977 Pertaining to the book reviews and permission issues., 45 pages. (Box-folder 2/52)
  - Long, Maud (Mrs.). February 12, 1971 Maud Long corresponds with Emrich as she prepares to host two interviewees being sent to her by Emrich., 5 pages. (Box-folder 2/53)
  - Mass Communications, Inc. August 9, 1973 Permission request to use audio recordings Duncan created in Nevada., 1 page. (Box-folder 2/54)
  - MacLeish, Archibald. 1968 Correspondence including poems., 5 pages. (Box-folder 2/55)
  - Mencken, H.L. December 31, 1945 Correspondence indicating the possibility of a meeting., 1 page. (Box-folder 2/56)
  - Mickey. July 15, 1967 Updating Emrich., 1 page. (Box-folder 2/57)
  - Montell, Lynwood. February 4, 1972 Lynwood informing Emrich that he wrote to the publishers on his behalf., 5 pages. (Box-folder 2/58)
  - Morrison, John W. April-June, 1968 Correspondence pertaining to Duncan Emrich joining the staff at the University of Nevada., 5 pages. (Box-folder 2/59)
  - Nagel, Charles. May 3, 1966 Pertaining to Gilbert Stuart portraits., 1 page. (Box-folder 2/60)
  - Nevada Highways and Parks Magazine. August 29, 1968 Poems Emrich submitted for publications which were subsequently returned., 3 pages. (Box-folder 2/61)
  - Newman, Heather. 1975-1976 Between Emrich and Newman about folklore., 9 pages (Box-folder 2/62)
  - Randolph, Vance. 1972 – 1974 Between Emrich’s and Randolph about folklore and possible reprints and permissions., 4 pages. (Box-folder 2/63)
  - Rath, Frederick L., Jr. June, 1967 Responding to Emrich’s request for materials., 2 pages. (Box-folder 2/64)
  - Richmond Organization, The- (Jay Mark, Vice Pres.). February 4, 1971 Concerning Emrich’s use of Frank Warner’s materials., 6 pages. (Box-folder 2/65)
  - Sarton, George. January 11, 1951 Concerning folkore publications and the passing of Mrs. George Sarton., 6 pages. (Box-folder 2/66)
  - Scyoc, Leo Van. May 25, 1977 Thank you letter., 1 page. (Box-folder 2/67)
  - Spadea Columns, Inc. (Stirling Spadea, Assoc. Ed). May 20, 1957 Information pertaining to being a columnist., 1 page. (Box-folder 2/68)
  - Tennessee Folklore Society (Ralph W. Hyde Sec. Ed.). February 21, 1972 Thank you letter pertaining to the receipt of Folklore on the American Land., 1 page. (Box-folder 2/69)
  - Texas Folklore Society (Wilson M. Hudson, Sec. Ed). December 23, 1970, Jan. 18, 1971 Permission request for Folklore on the American Land., 2 pages. (Box-folder 2/70)
  - Thomas Y. Crowell Company. November 16, 1960, March 12, 1971 Definition request and registration certificate for The Cowboy’s Own Brand Book., 4 pages. (Box-folder 2/71)
  - Thompson, Lawrence. March 15, 1971 Thompson requests permission to use material for his biography of Robert Frost., 1 page. (Box-folder 2/72)
  - Toelken, Barre. January 20, 1971 Pertaining the receipt of Henry Hyatt’s Hoodoo-Conjuration Withcraft- Rootwork for review and the request to receive Western Folklore., 1 page. (Box-folder 2/73)
  - Twane Publishers, Inc. 1967-1968 Concerning publishing fees., 10 pages. (Box-folder 2/74)
  - University of California Press. April 10, 1968 Pertaining to Comstock Bonanza., 15 pages. (Box-folder 2/75)
  - University of Oklahoma Press. July 12, 1967, January 30, 1971, February 3, 1971 Response to order and permission request from Emrich., 3 pages. (Box-folder 2/76)
  - University of Texas (Stephen H. Spurr. Pres). September 20, 1973 Thank you letter to Emrich for the deposit of materials he made to the World War II collection at the University., 1 page. (Box-folder 2/77)
  - University of Wisconsin (1971 Lewis Carroll Shelf Award). August 23, 1971 Award letter for The Nonsense Book., 1 page. (Box-folder 2/78)
  - Utley, Francis Lee. August 1967, June 1973 Pertaining to Emrich’s books on folklore., 5 pages (Box-folder 2/79)
  - Walt. March, 20, 1968, April 20, 1968 To Walt from Emrich concerning his future position at the University of Nevada., 2 pages. (Box-folder 2/80)